Last week, Builder AI, a UK-based startup, once valued at 1.5 billion,
backed by Microsoft and of course, SoftBank, has collapsed back to $0.
This comes at a time when literally all my friends are becoming billionaires by putting the
letters AI in front of their startup names, but the party can't go on forever.
Like most startups out there nowadays, Builder AI offered a vibe-coding platform called Builder Studio,
that promised to make you software without any technical expertise required.
But as it turns out, that promise is hard to keep in reality, and I kid you not,
their solution to half-ast AI code was instead to use a room full of underpaid Indian programmers
to massage the slop into a working demo. In other words, it's an artificial intelligence tool
powered by biological intelligence. As ridiculous as that sounds though,
it's not the main reason Builder AI collapsed. They were also engaging in outright fraud to make
their mirror go burr. In today's video, we'll find out what went wrong and what it means for the
future of AI coding startups. It is June 3rd, 2025, and you're watching the code report.
It's been a while, a few days, for the AI enthusiast. The Clawed 4 was released,
and it made Clawed 3.7 slightly better. Then just after that, DeepSeek R1 gets an update that
makes DeepSeek R1 slightly better. We're not talking about exponential runaway intelligence here,
which is kind of disappointing, but we'll take what we can get to keep the hype train going.
But maybe we'll go exponential soon, because a new paper just dropped, describing the
Darwin-Godell machine. A self-improving AI system that iteratively modifies its Python
codebase to validate its own coding capabilities on software engineering benchmarks using frozen
foundation models. It sounds kind of like Google Alpha code, but if it actually works, we really
are cooked this time. But if your goal is to make money, the most important lesson to remember is
that your tech doesn't actually need to work to get super rich. The Builder AI used that wisdom
to create a product that quickly went from 0 to 1.5 billion, then back to 0 again. And on the
website, they say we make building an app so easy that even a caveman can do it. The way it works is
that you prompt it just like Chatchy PT, then a professional human powered vibe coder steps in to
fix all the slopp. It's the perfect platform for people not talented enough to vibe code.
The problem though is that their approach doesn't scale, and apparently the roomful of Indian
programmers was doing more work than the AI. That's not a good look, but the main reason they went
bankrupt is that they were also committing outright fraud, allegedly, with a round-trip billing
scheme with one of their partners. They were invoicing for work they never did to make their
revenue go up. It's grower die, but unfortunately one of their creditors found out and sees $37
million from their bank accounts, and that let them no choice but to declare bankruptcy. It seems
like everywhere you go on the internet right now, you'll find Clueless Optimists is saying that 90
percent of white color work will be eliminated by AI within the next five years, to which the Clueless
pessimist respond by saying that AI is nothing more than the latest Silicon Valley pyramid scheme.
The truth is likely somewhere in the middle, and it's going to be fun to watch this bubble pop
like 2001 or explode into the singularity. Either way it's a win, but the best way to get the most out
of these AI tools is to learn how they work under the hood, and you can start doing that today for
free thanks to this video sponsor, Brilliant. There how AI WorkScore teaches you how to build your
own language model from scratch is starting with simple text prediction before scaling up to more
advanced topics like image manipulation. Each lesson is designed to be highly interactive as you
develop critical thinking skills through problem solving, not memorizing. But try everything brilliant
has to offer for free for 30 days by visiting brilliant.org slash fireship or scan the QR code on
screen to get 20 percent off a premium annual subscription. This has been the code report, thanks for
watching and I will see you in the next one.